William D. Hersey Papers MS039
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
William D. Hersey Papers
1941 -- 2001
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Hersey, William D.
Hersey, Harry Adams
MS039
6.76 Linear Feet
This collection primarily contains research materials related to the "Fame is Fleeting-Character Endures" memorial plaque project spearheaded by William D. Hersey, providing information about individuals for whom buildings are named at Tufts University. Hersey graduated from Tufts with a degree in psychology in 1932. Additional materials include personal and professional correspondences of Harry Adams Hersey, William's father, and William D. Hersey's subject files on careers, co-education, engineering, and rehabilitation services at Tufts.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in two series: Papers; and Plaques.
Scope and Contents
This collection primarily contains research materials related to the "Fame is Fleeting-Character Endures" memorial plaque project spearheaded by William D. Hersey. Included are Hersey's research notes and material about individuals after whom Tufts buildings were named, as well as a copy of the texts of the final plaques based on this material.
The collection also contains correspondence, clippings and and handwritten notes as well as publications and advertisements for Tufts events. Additional materials include personal and professional correspondences of Harry Adams Hersey, William's father, and William D. Hersey's subject files on careers, co-education, engineering, and rehabilitation services at Tufts.
Biographical / Historical
William Dearborn Hersey A'32, was born December 3, 1910. He studied psychology at Tufts and married Fairlee (Towsley) Hersey J'35. He became the president of the International Memory Training Institute in Norton, Massachusetts, and published Blueprints for Memory: Your Handbook to the American Dream in 1990.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Hersey, William Dearborn; Hersey, Harry Adams; Alumni and alumnae; Plaques --Buildings; Music; University history
- Papers, 1941 -- 2001; 1931 -- 1995; MS039.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series primarily contains research materials related to the "Fame is Fleeting-Character Endures" memorial plaque project spearheaded by William D. Hersey. This series contains Hersey's research notes and material about individuals after whom Tufts buildings were named, as well as a copy of the texts of the final plaques based on this material.
  Correspondence, clippings and and handwritten notes are included as well as publications and advertisements for Tufts events.
  Additional materials include personal and professional correspondences of Harry Adams Hersey, William's father, and William D. Hersey's subject files on careers, co-education, engineering, and rehabilitation services at Tufts.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically. Final text and correspondence of Harry Adams Hersey are included at the end.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Academic Work Sheets, MS039.001.001.00001; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Letter to the Tufts Daily
    Hersey, William Dearborn
  - Ackerman '97 (Gary L.), MS039.001.001.00002; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Clippings, biographic information, and business cards relating to Gary L. Ackerman
  - Aidekman (Aidekman, Alex and Shirley), MS039.001.001.00003; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Correspondence and clippings regarding the Aidekman Arts Center and the Charles Koppelman lower gallery.
    Aidekman, Alex
  - Alumnae Hall, 1941; MS039.001.001.00004; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Alumni Bulletin from May 1941
  - Alumni Council, 1996; MS039.001.001.00005; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Correspondence and Alumni Council Agenda 1996
  - Alumni Doc, MS039.001.001.00006; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Primarily correspondence regarding Fame is Fleeting -- Character Endures building plaques
  - Alumni Reunion, 1996; MS039.001.001.00007; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    1996 correspondence regarding change of date for Alumni Weekend including with Tufts' president
  - Bacon (Bacon, George P.), MS039.001.001.00009; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including correspondence, historical note and handwritten notes
    Bacon, George Preston
  - Balch (Balch, Marston -- Arena), MS039.001.001.00010; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including historical note, clippings, correspondence, and _Spotlight on the Hill Tufts Arena Theater: The First 50 Years_)
    Balch, Marston Stevens
  - Ballou, MS039.001.001.00011; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including excepts from _Ballous in America_
  - Barnum (P.T.), MS039.001.001.00012; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including letters to Harry Adams Hersey regarding Barnum memorials and manuscripts, notes and clippings on Barnum and Jumbo, publication on Jumbo by H.A. Hersey, _P.T. Barnum's Jumbo_ by Russell L. Carpenter (2 copies -- one autographed by H.A. Hersey), Barnum Festival clippings and programs, biography of H.A. Hersey for sermon given at Barnum festival and the sermon, and "Why I Am a Universalist" by P. T. Barnum
    Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor)
  - Baronian (John -- Field House), MS039.001.001.00013; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including notes, clippings, correspondence, biographical information, and Tufts Jumbo Club 1969-1994 25th Anniversary and Annual Awards Dinner Program (2 copies)
    Baronian, John
  - Becker (Edward) -- Dental School, MS039.001.001.00014; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including correspondence, notes and biographical information
    Becker, Edward
  - Bendetson (Admissions Center), MS039.001.001.00015; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    1 of 2 Subject file including Bendetson Admissions Center historical note
  - Bendetson (Admissions Center), MS039.001.001.00016; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    2 of 2 Subject file including correspondence, clippings, and historical note
  - Blakesley (Gerald W., Jr.), MS039.001.001.00017; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including biographic information on Gerald W. Blakesley, Jr.
  - Bolles (Edward C.), MS039.001.001.00018; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including historical note, lecture by E. C. Bolles, correspondence, and biographical information
    Bolles, Edwin Courtlandt
  - Bowen (Eugene B.), MS039.001.001.00019; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including clipping (see also Dolbear)
    Bowen, Eugene B.
  - Bray (Charles) -- Laboratory, MS039.001.001.00020; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including historical note and biographical information
    Bray, Charles Durlin
  - Bush-Vann (Vannevar, Perry, and Edith Bush), MS039.001.001.00021; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including clippings, correspondence, copies of patent sheets, articles and biographical information. Also includes papers on William H. Ryder
    Bush, Vannevar
  - Careers, MS039.001.001.00022; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including publications and clippings on getting the most from a college education and succeeding post-graduation including works by William D. Hersey
  - Carmichael (Leonard), MS039.001.001.00023; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Clipping and history of the Leonard Carmichael Society
    Carmichael, Leonard
  - Carmichael Society, MS039.001.001.00024; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including handwritten notes
  - Citations, MS039.001.001.00025; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Texts from multiple honorary award citations speeches
  - Co-Education, MS039.001.001.00026; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Article by Cecelia Van Auken _1892-Co-Education at Tufts-1942_
  - Cohen (Edward E.) -- Art Center, MS039.001.001.00027; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including historical note, correspondence, and clippings
    Cohen, Edward E.
  - Coolidge Room (Coolidge, Robert T.) -- in Ballou Hall, MS039.001.001.00028; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including correspondence, biographical information and historical note
    Coolidge, Robert Tilton
  - Cousens (John) -- Gymnasium, MS039.001.001.00029; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including noe and biographical information
    Cousens, John Albert
  - Curtis (James O.), MS039.001.001.00030; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including biographical note, correspondence and clippings
    Curtis, James Otis
  - Dana Lab (Charles) -- Laboratory, MS039.001.001.00031; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including correspondence, biographic information, and a clipping
    Dana, Charles A.
  - Dewick (Cora Polk), MS039.001.001.00032; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including honorary degree information and clippings
    Dewick, Cora Polk
  - Dolbear (Amos Emerson), MS039.001.001.00033; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including biographical information and correspondence. See also Bowen file
    Dolbear, Amos Emerson
  - Dranetz (Abraham and Marianna) -- Science and Technology Center, MS039.001.001.00034; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including biographical information and clippings and development information
  - Eliot Pearson (Eliot, Abigail Adams and Pearson, Elizabeth Winsor), MS039.001.001.00035; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including _A Heart of Grateful Trust: Memoirs of Abigail Adams Eliot_ transcribed and edited by Marjorie Gott Manning (who has a letter in Aidekman folder), biographical information, correspondence, _Abigail Eliot and the nursery school movement_ by Manning and _Nursery Schools Fifty Years Ago_ by Eliot
    Eliot, Abigail A.
  - Engineering -- Music, MS039.001.001.00036; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including program from 1995 One-Hundreth Year Celebration Concert honoring Dr. T. J. Anderson, and a Tufts Engineering pamphlet
  - Fay, Charles Ernest, MS039.001.001.00037; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including article on Fay by Harry A. Hersey, _Charles Ernest Fay 1846-1931_ by William Howell Reed and clipping
    Fay, Charles Ernest
  - Fletcher (Austin Barclay), MS039.001.001.00038; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including _Initiating professional education in internation relations: The Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, 1923-1943_ by Timothy Benjamin Brown (Thesis), biographical information, clippings, correspondence, photos of Murrow Center plaques, scultpure and paintings
    Fletcher, Austin Barclay
  - Foster (Henry) -- Veterinary School, MS039.001.001.00039; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including corrspondence, clippings, and historical note
    Foster, Henry L.
  - Hall House (Frank Oliver), MS039.001.001.00040; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including historical note, and except from "And they neighbor as thyself" by Emerson Hugh Lalone
    Hall, Frank Oliver
  - Hallowell (Burton), MS039.001.001.00041; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including clipping
    Hallowell, Burton Crosby
  - Hamilton (Frederick William), MS039.001.001.00042; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including clipping and biographical information
    Hamilton, Frederick William
  - Bill Hersey (William Dearborn), MS039.001.001.00043; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including clippings, correspondence, service citation from Tufts Alumni, "Tufts sports: A proving ground for life" by Paul Sweeney and photos
  - Holmes (John), MS039.001.001.00044; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including correspondence, clippings and copies of poems "Along the row" and "The Fence", and historical note
    Holmes, John
  - Hooper (William Leslie), MS039.001.001.00045; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including historical note, clippings, and biographical information
    Hooper, William Leslie
  - Houston, MS039.001.001.00046; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Handwritten note
  - Jackson (Henry Clay), MS039.001.001.00047; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including biographical information, historical note, correspondence, and clippings
    Jackson, Henry Clay
  - Johansen (Erling), MS039.001.001.00048; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including copy of retirement letter and clippings and CV and bibliographic information
    Johansen, Erling
  - Jumbo, MS039.001.001.00049; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including _P.T. Barnum's Jumbo_ by Russell L. Carpenter
    Jumbo
  - Leir (Henry J.), MS039.001.001.00050; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including historical note, correspondence, and biographical data
    Leir, Henry J.
  - Lewis (Leo Rich), MS039.001.001.00051; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file includings biographical information and a clipping
    Lewis, Leo R.
  - Lewis and H A Hersey, MS039.001.001.00052; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including _H.A. Hersey, Genial Crusader_, poem by John Holmes on Leo Rich Lewis, _The Christian Leader_ from October 1945 with a story on Lewis by Hersey (multiple photocopies also)
  - Leo Lewis, 1943; MS039.001.001.00053; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including article from the January 1943 Tuftonian "Grand Old Man" by Pauline Moyer and John Holmes, handwritten letter from H.A. Hersey to Lewis, "Forward, Tufts! March" with song-trio music by Lewis, "Three Cheers for Uncle Sam" sheet music, clippings and three copies of _The Christian Leader_
  - MacJannet, MS039.001.001.00054; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including clippings and correspondence plus information on Mary van Bibber Harris
    MacJannet, Donald Ross
  - MacPhie (Elmore and Etta), MS039.001.001.00055; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including correspondence, biographical information, historical note, text of honorary doctorate speech for MacPhie
    MacPhie, Elmore I.; MacPhie, Etta
  - Mayer (Jean and Elizabeth Van Huysen Mayer), MS039.001.001.00056; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including historical note, correspondence, clippings, "Jean Mayer Chair in Nutrition" ceremony remarks and program, program for the Elizabeth Van Huysen Mayer Campus Center -- also some Leir materials
    Mayer, Elizabeth Van Huysen; Mayer, Jean
  - Medical--Dental, MS039.001.001.00057; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file containing clippings on multiple people involved with the Tufts' Medical and Dental schools
  - Men of Science, MS039.001.001.00058; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file containing biographical information on multiple people from the Tuftonian
  - Meserve (Robert), MS039.001.001.00059; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file containing correspondence and a clipping
    Meserve, Robert W.
  - Michael (Arthur G.), MS039.001.001.00060; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file containing historical note, biographical information, clipping and correspondence
    Michael, Arthur
  - Music, 1991; MS039.001.001.00061; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including _Tufts in Song_, proposed lyrics for "Alma Mater" song, and correspondence regarding concert in 1990/1991
  - Nickless (Fred), MS039.001.001.00062; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including information on Seymour Merrin, Robert Nichols, and Fred Nickless -- clippings and biographical information including handwritten notes
    Nichols, Robert L.
  - Olin (Franklin W.), MS039.001.001.00063; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including clippings and corrspondence
  - Pearson (Frederick Stark), MS039.001.001.00064; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including letter and biographical information
    Pearson, Fred Stark
  - Pound (Roscoe), MS039.001.001.00065; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including biographical information and correspondence
    Pound, Roscoe
  - Products by Tufts, MS039.001.001.00066; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file on innovations developed at Tufts
  - Rehabililitation, MS039.001.001.00067; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including publications of the Department of Rehabililitation Medicine at Tufts regarding childhood injuries
  - Research, MS039.001.001.00068; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including copies of informationon multiple people, _Selected Tufts Buildings: Their Names and History_ by Christine Melich, correspondence and notes
  - Richardson (D. Kenneth and Constance Rogers), MS039.001.001.00069; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including biographical information, correspondence, historical note, and clippings
  - Robinson (Charles), MS039.001.001.00070; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file inclduing historical note for Robinson Hall and Curtis Hall
  - Sackler (Arthur M.), MS039.001.001.00071; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including corrspondence, historical notes, and clippings
    Sackler, Arthur M.
  - Sawyer (William Jefferson), MS039.001.001.00072; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including historical note
  - Starr King (Thomas), MS039.001.001.00073; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including handwritten notes regarding various people, _Thomas Starr King: The Man Behind the Legend_ by Arnold Crompton, biographical information and correspondence
  - Sweet (Harold E.), MS039.001.001.00074; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including clippings and biographical information
    Sweet, Harold E.
  - Tisch, MS039.001.001.00075; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    1 of 2, Subject file including library dedication artical in the Tuftonia, clippings and biographical information, and Program of Events from library opening
  - Tisch, 1994; MS039.001.001.00076; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    2 of 2, Subject file including clippings and correspondence, program from Parent's Weekend 1994, Tufts' publications regarding the library and the groundbreaking program
  - Tishler (Max), MS039.001.001.00077; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including corrspondence and clippings
    Tishler, Max
  - Tomlinson (Irving Clinton), MS039.001.001.00078; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including article by H. A. Hersey
    Tomlinson, Irving
  - Wren (Frank G.), MS039.001.001.00079; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Subject file including correspondence and photo of the photo of the building groundbreaking
    Wren, Frank G.
  - Wessell (Nils), MS039.001.001.00080; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Wessell, Nils Yngve
  - William Hersey - Historical plaque text, MS039.001.001.00081; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Completed texts of all Domitory and Building plague statements
  - Correspondence, MS039.001.001.00082; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Letter which was originally loose in box
  - Information Issues, MS039.001.001.00083; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 1)
    Publication which was originally loose in box
  - Hersey, Henry Adams, 1941 -- 1972; MS039.001.001.00084; Hersey, Harry Adams (Box 1)
    Vertical file folder added to box including typed postcards, correspondence -- both person and professional -- 1941-1951, 1972 regarding Univeralist Church, Music History at Tufts, and William D. Hersey's schooling at Tufts, small photo of Mrs. Harry (Lottie I.) Hersey, and correspondence of Helen Hersey Dick (daughter) and Lottie I. (wife)
    Hersey, Harry Adams
  - Versling/Hersey, MS039.001.001.00085 (Box 1)
    Vertical file folder added to box including correspondence, article and the poem "The Versling" by Harry Adams Hersey
  - History of the Class of 1903 by Harry Adams Hersey, MS039.001.001.00086; Hersey, Harry Adams (Box 1)
  - The First Universalist College in the World by Harry Adams Hersey, MS039.001.001.00087; Hersey, Harry Adams (Box 1)
  - The "Meaningful to Youth" Memorial Plaques at Tufts University: historical notes researched and composed by William D. Hersey, A32, 2001 May; MS039.000096 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Harry Adams Hersey Tufts watch fob, circa 1900s; MS039.000097; 1 Items (Box 1)
    Tufts watch fob worn by Harry Adams Hersey. Harry Adams Hersey entered Tufts in 1899, graduated in 1903, and received post-baccalaureate degree in 1907. He wrote 'History of Music at Tufts College' in 1940. He served on the Tufts Department of Music faculty and was a Universalist reverend. Additionally, he carried out research on P. T. Barnum and other Universalists. William Dearborn Hersey was his son.
  - "First Universalist College in the World" by Henry Adams Hersey, 1943; MS039.000098 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Accession MS-2023-014
- Plaques, 1994; MS039.002; 3.6 Linear Feet
  This series contains plaques related to the "Fame is Fleeting-Character Endures" memorial project spearheaded by William Hersey. Plaques were affixed to campus buildings to provide historical context for regarding their donors. Some plaques were removed for construction projects and transferred to the DCA.
  This series is arranged by content.
  - Along the Row plaque, 1994; MS039.002.002.00001; Holmes, John (Box 2)
  - Tufts Traditions plaque, 1994; MS039.002.002.00002; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 2)
  - Elizabeth Van Huysen Mayer Campus Center plaque, 1994; MS039.002.003.00001; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 3)
  - Why Tufts? plaque, 1994; MS039.002.003.00002; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 3)
  - Crusader for Mankind plaque, 1994; MS039.002.004.00001; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 4)
    Mayer, Jean
  - The Freedom Fighter's Legacy plaque, 1994; MS039.002.004.00002; Hersey, William Dearborn (Box 4)